Rich, Michael, welcome back to Talk Python to Me. Awesome to have you both back on the show.
Yeah, thanks for having us.
Yeah, for sure. We're going to talk about great things. I know it's going to be a great show.
It's undoubtable, right?
I have no doubt.
It's a great day, you know, and we're ready for I think what's going to be a great chat.
Yeah.
About great docs, great tables, all of those things.
All the great things.
Yeah. So I had you on to talk about Great Tables, which was really fun. You're both from Posit.
And other than that, maybe let's do a quick introduction for folks. I mean, I don't know
why anybody would not have listened to the Great Tables episode, but in case they haven't. No,
honestly, we get a bunch of new listeners all the time. So yeah, let's do a quick
round of introductions. Who are you? What do you do? Why are you working on this project?
Rich, start with you.
Yeah. Yeah, I'm Rich. I work at Posit, PVC. I've been doing traditionally lots of R stuff,
like in the past. But more lately, this is like the last three or four years, a lot more Python
stuff. And actually, Michael, who's with me today, he taught me a lot about Python. Like, I was
pretty bad starting. I mean, I used in the past, but I was open source stuff. I was,
ugh, I was bad. Michael has so much patience, though. So he helped me get up to speed over
a period of a year or so. So I owe a lot to him. And he's a great guy.
That's really cool. I agree with that.
I think it's hard to change a language. It's hard to switch to another language. And maybe
you could speak to that real quick before Michael jumps in. And just, I've done that
a couple of times. You know, you spend so much time and energy and effort and getting
really good at, not just the language, the tools, the ecosystem, everything.
And then you're like, I'm 1.0. I think I have to go over there for a while.
Yeah, it feels like a bizarre situation. Like, I know what I could be doing, what I should be
doing, like, theoretically. But things just don't jive sometimes. It's like, oh, yeah. But then you
get used to it. And then your previous language degrades. It's kind of like that sort of thing.
It's a little bit sad in that regard. But for me, the real challenge was, I have such a deep
knowledge and mastery of this technology. And if I switch, at least the first time or two I did,
I felt like, I'm going to go back to the noobiest of noobs. And it's going to feel really bad. And
I worked so hard for this knowledge and this experience. Why am I going to do this? Maybe I
should never do that. It was a big deal for me. I want to say that for other people out there who
are not necessarily going R to Python, but just one tech to another.
Yeah, it's humbling, like I said. And well, with a good mentor and lots of patience,
it can happen.
Yeah, it's good to expand your skills. But the initial decision is rough.
Michael, you've been shepherding Rich along the way. I love it. Tell us about yourself.
Yeah, I wouldn't even say shepherding. Or maybe there's some mutual shepherding going on.
So I'm Michael Chow. I'm a software engineer at Posit and have been for about four years on the
open source team. So I've worked with Rich on things like great tables.
And I think that, yeah, I'm really interested in Python. I work on Python full time.
And I think if I had to send back what Rich is really good at, Rich just has this crazy,
freaky sense of style. And I think that's one thing that's drawn me to work with him on things
is you just never know. Like, to be totally honest, people at Posit just never know what
Rich is going to pull out. And I don't think any of us could have imagined it. He's our wildcard.
And it's been interesting because you can imagine like a programming language.
Yeah, you could be like, oh, this person taught me this programming language.
I don't really know how you teach Rich's style, but I feel like I'm kind of along for the ride.
I'm like eating popcorn, helping out. And I think tools like Great Docs really reflect that, this
interesting sense of style. Like Great Tables, he's just dipped into this rich history of table
styling. How would you style it to present and maybe publish it? And so I've been excited to be
along for the ride to just watch him cook and bring this unique sense of style and design into
tools. Yeah, that's really cool. Certain people just have a knack for APIs and the way that
developer UX sort of thing. That's cool. I personally am excited for the mascot.
The mascots.
Rich, I blew your cover. So Michael and I were talking a little bit at PyCon
about Tablin, how you're a mascot wizard. Who is Tablin, though, I wonder?
He's just a little table guy, a little table dude, that appears, gives you help,
and then disappears just as fast. He doesn't fully realize that.
He's always thinking of you. He's never thinking of himself. He's showing up, helping you out.
He's like the new Libby or Bob, but much cooler because he's a table.
And I do think this speaks to our dynamic where Tablin just appeared one day. While we were
preparing a PyCon talk two years ago, Tablin just appeared in the slides, and I didn't know who
Tablin was, and I was like, who or what is this? It was like a slide of a table, and Tablin was
popped out on the side, was saying, good job. And I was like, who's this spreadsheet with eyes and a
mouth cheering people on? And Rich was like, it's Tablin, of course.
Yeah, it's helpful to have a little dude that just wants to help.
It's like having a pet, like a cat.
I love it. That's really good. So Michael, we had the great opportunity to meet up at PyCon
just last week. I don't know how you feel about it personally. I'm still just a little bit
recovering from the whole energy that was extracted from me, but it was really fun.
Maybe just give us your thoughts on PyCon and how'd that go?
Yeah, it's a great question. It's so interesting because we work on tools for data analysis,
but PyCon is much more general. It's almost like all things Python. I think it's a really
interesting conference versus like a PyData or a SciPy, which are way oriented towards like
data tools specifically. But I love it. I find it really nice to be able to drop in and talk to
just the full range of Python people who maybe have never used or done a lot of data analysis.
So I find it really interesting to talk to folks who maybe almost universally, I think everybody
has touched Pandas, the library for data frames. And so that's the funny point you can always talk
to anyone about at PyCon. But I find it really nice and I find the PyCon organizers and the
Python Software Foundation, it's just so down to earth that, yeah, I really love dropping in. It
doesn't feel super corporate. It feels like they're really a group of passionate volunteers
putting this pretty big conference on. So yeah, I always love dropping in, even if it's a broader
audience than the data crew. I'm curious, your experience, have you gone to a lot of PyCons?
I think my first one, when was my first? Mid-teens, I would say 2015, 2016, something like that.
Yeah, nice. I'd probably have gone to maybe two thirds since then, most. I mean, we did have
COVID in the middle, that was challenging. But yeah, I've been to a fair number and I really
enjoy it. And for me, it's just nice to get together, meet folks like you and everyone else
and just kind of remember, hey, this is a community of humans and not just docs. I mean, docs are
great. We're going to talk about how great docs can be, but it's also nice to just have these
human connections and just connect with people outside of width, but also outside of technology.
Hey, let's just go sit in the sun for a while and talk. Have you seen the sun lately? No,
I haven't seen it either. Let's go sit there. All day, yeah. Yeah, for real. I feel like it is.
Just putting the face behind the name or actually touching down to chat does seem like a huge
thing that you only do like, say, once or twice a year with those folks.
Yeah, at least for me, I can come back and revitalize to do more. So that's really,
really sweet. Let's start our journey here talking about, let's just do a quick
review of Great Tables. Because I know Great Tables was one of the inspirations for Great
Docs. All three of us got together last year, I guess, to talk about Great Tables. So who wants
to just do a quick reminder of this one? I'll go. So basically, yeah, Great Tables,
it's maybe not being people notice, it's a port of an R package called GT.
Not that important, but the idea is good as it was then. You want display tables,
what I call them, essentially summary tables, like static tables. And you want to present them,
say, in a notebook or, say, in some other publishable document as HTML. We also have
a LaTeX output format. But the idea is you compose tables step by step. You add a header,
you want a title, you get that too. You structure the table. You can format different cells,
like usually entire columns of cells. And you can also style a table, which could be like changing
orders, adding cell backgrounds, things like that. And really, the idea is to make a table
that you might see in a print publication, but using your data directly, using a data frame.
So you have the data in a form which is amenable to a summary table. And then in just a few method
calls, you've got the table. You know what's, yeah, that's awesome. What strikes me about this?
Um, you know, when we had our conversation last year, it's just how much more there is to think
about with tables than, you know, just an Excel-like thing. I came away realizing that
it goes way deeper, and there's a lot more nuance. It felt a little bit like, oh gosh,
I can't remember the guy's name, but I'm sure you both have seen his books, but it's...
Is his name Tufty?
No, no, no, Tufty. Tufty, yes. He's just like, oh, I see, like there's some lines and stuff. Like,
no, no, no, no, hold on. There's a lot going on. Like, there's many things you can communicate
subtly without just being like, well, let's just call this out. Like, no, you don't even have to
call it out. It's communicated through something more interesting. You know, Tufty is that about
just presenting sort of scientific information in general, but I felt that way about tables as well.
Yeah, it's pretty well. We talked about this in our talk a few years back in PyCon,
how you can tell a story with a table, where you can communicate data in a better way,
not a more optimized way, but a more legible way, where your main point is described like a title
and a subtitle, and you have notes at the bottom, and you can guide people through
an analysis summary that way. And so just like with many different things, there's a good way
to do it, or a better way to do it. Yeah, you could just look at certain
types of presented information, and go, well, that looks really professional, or that looks
really, really good, but I don't know why. You know what I mean?
Yeah. That was good, but I can't put my finger on exactly what is really different,
but that's really good, and that's not. And I feel like great tables kind of leans into that.
Yeah, I guess it takes the Tufty principle to having just the right amount of ink, I guess,
like not too much, just enough to communicate the structure of things, like the architecture
of the data you're laying out, and not doing much more of that. So there's a lot of that
that goes into this. Indeed.
As a default thing. Yeah.
To the Tufty point, too, Tufty's website, Tufty has like all of these just dumps of examples,
just like example plot, example plot, example plot. It's almost like a very rough notebook,
and I feel like with great tables, it was kind of similar, like when I first came on, I knew
basically nothing about this topic, and I saw the components of the table diagram, so you have it
pulled up, but it has like a table broken apart into all its pieces, like a title, subtitle.
There's this funny thing called the stubhead and spanners, and I thought, like, does a person
really need to know all this? But I think to the point of Tufty, like maybe what you're getting
at, too, is Tufty really dives into like very specific, almost like dimensions of how you could
represent data. One thing he gets really into is like spark lines, this idea that like how far
could you get with a line that basically doesn't have any axis labels, but it's just like a trend,
like is it going up or is it going down? And that happens a lot in tables, you'll put like
these spark lines in a cell, like if you're looking at stocks, you'll have like the stock
numbers, and then you'll have a spark line that like indicates the kind of trend,
so people can grab it really fast. But I find what's interesting about Tufty is just that
willingness to dive in so detailed about this one very specific action, and I feel like this
table diagram is sort of similar to me, the willingness to like break it apart so thoroughly.
At first, I wasn't really convinced. It seemed like a lot of work, but yeah, I think to your
point about Tufty, once you start looking at examples, you start to realize this kind of
captures the like flavor or design of like good examples out there in the world.
Yeah, I think it's really out there. Like initially, my idea, too, is like, oh, is this too
much? But naming things is so important, otherwise you're just awkwardly describing something over and
over again, like that cell to the top left or these cells off to the side. And eventually,
you just have to give it a name, even if it's not the best name. And it's actually names I stole
from like basically a census manual on tables, I think written in 1949. Great ideas, like
wonderful book, and it's on the web as a PDF still. It's a scam.
Yeah, I remember I was talking about that.
Yeah, really good stuff.
How interesting is it? Yeah, how interesting is it that
the inspiration comes from pre-digital times?
Yeah, because a lot of the software produces some of these ideas. It's like, well, I have grids.
I have a grid of cells, and sometimes the rows can be taller. Sometimes you can span a row. Okay,
that's that. But if you just write it by hand, when you have to way back in the day,
it's like, oh, well, maybe we could draw it differently, right?
Yeah. Yeah, it's like I was searching, researching anything on tables I could find just to get ideas
and what people thought was good. And it's really hard to find anything on tables. It's like, oh,
but I did find that one thing, and I'm forever in debt to the person who wrote it.
Yeah, that's awesome. So let's move on. But if people are out there, and they're
doing presentations that involve tables, and especially if it's code generating those tables,
check this out. It's quite interesting. So the next thing I want to talk about is just
surveying the landscape of what is out there. Because we're going to talk about great docs,
and great docs can generate static sites. There's some existing tools that generate docs
as static sites. There's some really good tools that just generate static sites that maybe people
could put into docs. There's a lot of things that are somewhat similar. There's also stuff that's
in the same space, but different. So maybe we could kind of go through and, you know, like,
I know you all have mentioned Sphinx is a real popular one in the Python space.
There's mkdocs. I had Martin from Zenzicle on not too long ago. So maybe we could talk
first about some of the existing tools that are, I guess, as similar as possible to what you're
doing. Yeah. Michael, would you like to speak on this? Because I know you did a deep dive recently
on these. Yeah. So Sphinx, I think, and maybe to kick off some helpful context to great docs is
that, yeah, I worked a lot on early support for documentation with a tool called QuarterDoc.
But Rich actually took it to the next level. And this goes to, I think, Rich's style
with great docs. So I have a lot of bizarre, like, experience looking at the history of Python docs.
And I think Sphinx is one of the OG site builders. I can't I think this is the case.
So I think one interesting fact is, as I understand it, I think Python.org,
don't quote me on this, I think it was originally done in, like, LaTeX or something like that,
the Python docs. And I think that they moved to Sphinx at some point. So, like,
Sphinx has a really interesting history in Python. Like, if you go back 25, 30 years,
Python docs had to exist using some tool, right? And at some point Sphinx emerged as kind of like
this dominant site builder for Python and Python docs. Yeah, does it say? Yeah. So
Python docs are in Sphinx. You know, this Python doc site has a how-to, Python how-tos.
This is another weird fact. The how-tos emerged, I don't remember exactly when they emerged. It
was, like, in the last 30 years, I think, as part of the Linux project. So the term how-to,
as I understand it, emerged in the Linux docs. But all these things, like, it's so funny,
we see them today and maybe it seems we just think about, like, oh, there's the Python docs.
But actually at a certain point, you know, Sphinx emerged, this concept of a how-to emerged.
These are all things that over the last, I think, like, 30 years sort of, like,
came into existence. So Sphinx is like the OG doc site. A lot of tools use it. Pandas uses it
to generate its APIs. Polars uses it as well. So some really big Python tools use it to generate
their API docs. It uses this thing called restructured text. I will say, like, I don't
know that a lot of open tool developers love it. I want to be a bit careful here because I think
it's been so useful. But I do think that restructured text is kind of not the thing
most open source developers are reaching for these days. But Sphinx is, like, the OG
doc site. And it powers a ton of docs like Python.org and Pandas.
Yeah. I'm sure if, you know, I'm sure it was really made a huge improvement when it came out,
though, right? If you're doing a lot of tech before, that's got to be pretty rough.
Yeah. It's like zero to one, essentially, I think, switching from the tech to Sphinx for, like,
your Python docs.
Yeah. And if I see an RST file, just a little tear wells up in my eye. I'm like, oh, gosh,
here we go.
It's almost like a rite of passage, I feel like. Like, as a Python developer producing docs
in the, like, Sphinx world, you just kind of, like, I learned Sphinx and RST to generate docs,
essentially. It's like, yeah, I feel like that was my rite of passage into, like, software
development.
Yeah. 100%. So, we've also got mkdocs, or mkdocs, probably. I don't know. I always feel like...
I say mkdocs, but I have no... So, I mean, you had the Zensucle people, so I feel like they...
Do you have a read on it?
If I try to remember, I feel like Martin said mkdocs, but...
He could have easily said mkdocs, and I was not paying attention.
I'm a main doctor, so...
Yeah, no, I think that makes sense. A lot of these that could be said one way or another,
I really wish, and maybe this does, but I really wish on their GitHub repo, they just have a
little mp3, like, here's how you say it. You know what I mean?
A little audio button.
Yeah, exactly. Like, green unicorn, like, g-unicorn versus goonicorn is, like,
one that I think goes around and around still.
So, Zensucle is one of the more modern ones. So, I think that that's pretty interesting.
Honestly, I'm not sure how much it lands in the Sphinx mkdocs world, or in the other,
maybe the just pure static site generator side of things.
So, yeah, go ahead.
The Zensucle folks came on and probably have the best sense, but my sense is it's also
meant to be kind of a, it might be ROM drop-in replacement for mkdocs. I know they're community.
Yeah, yeah, it is a compatibility, at least compatible for a material for mkdocs.
Yeah, right, right, right, right.
Yeah, for sure. So, yeah, I would say it's in that realm.
It also seems like they're heading towards general purpose or knowledge bases, which goes
maybe a bit beyond just like...
Yes, exactly. That was my, like, uncertainty is how do I classify it, right? Because it's,
it doesn't even necessarily, if you look at their H2, it doesn't say the best way to
make your docs, right? It's a scalable way for technical writing, which makes it, I think,
land a little more in the Hugo or Ghost side of things. So, that's another part to talk
about is just like static sites in general, you know, why would I choose, say, Sphinx
over Hugo or Hugo over Sphinx or something like that?
Yeah, it seems a bit like Mintlify. They have the same sort of thing going to, they do
documentation sites, but they go a bit beyond. It's like general purpose, lots of different
languages supported, but it is documentation, but not really so much like a site, like just
general purpose site generator.
Right, so Hugo and Ghost, I don't know Ghost very well, but Hugo, for example, I use that a lot for
blogs. I've seen one of my friends does really cool stuff just in general with Hugo, making
general purpose sites. I feel like this is much more focused on, I just need a static site and
much less, I need it to read my doc strings and categorize my modules and API calls and put in
that kind of stuff, right? So, that's another realm that is similar to what you all are doing,
but certainly not the same.
Yeah, if you want to throw another one in, there's Korto by the company we work at, Posit,
and that does sites and much more beyond.
I do think, yeah, I had JJ on, and I'm so sorry, I'm forgetting the name of the other
guy I had on.
Oh, Charles.
Yeah, I think it was Charles.
Oh, cool.
To talk about Korto a little while ago. That was fun.
Yeah, I do think a lot of the questions with Hugo versus something more targeted at docs for a tool
is hitting on what are the parts of a doc site? What's technical writing versus package
documentation? Am I just doing a Hugo thing? Is what I'm doing similar enough to a blog or a
website with content, which is really common? My website's in Hugo, or do I need something
special to dump out my API docs to dump out the things from my functions and classes?
Or could I jam that into Hugo? That's a common kind of hybrid path. Could my thing just dump my
info into Hugo? It's all kind of this dance between, is this a general content problem?
Is this a very specific tool problem? Or can I jam them both together into something?
Yeah, that's an interesting problem. So maybe a good time to start talking about great docs.
What is it? What's its value prop and positioning with regard to these other areas?
Well, on your screen, you have package down.
Yes, it's an origin.
It actually comes from R. I can't help but to be a little bit influenced by package down. I use it
a lot in my R projects. And it kind of felt like there was a package down sized hole in the Python
docs ecosystem, just a little bit, where you can just point something at your docs and it makes
something pretty fast with pretty much no configuration. That's the challenge. Does it
present something that's serviceable, usable right away? And that's what I was shooting for. And I
think that's kind of where I landed. And of course, we have tons of options to do way more things.
But I wanted to give something that was, you just start it right away and it gives you something.
For instance, you have doc strings and such, and they all just get captured and put into the API
reference section. And then later on, you would attend to it and organize it and then arrange it
and exclude things. At the very beginning, it would just give you something at least.
So that was kind of my goal, I think.
Yeah, the up and running super quick is one of the themes, right?
Yeah, absolutely. Because I suspect maybe a lot of people are getting more into Python
now because of agents, AI, LLMs, and such, and are spinning up small projects.
And maybe they're even building their documentation sites with using the same things like LLMs.
So getting something up quickly, and maybe the project doesn't last very long. It's just
like something just to get going. And you don't want to spend a ton of time on learning the docs,
a new doc system. So this sort of thing is pretty valuable. But we still give you the opportunity,
of course, to add things and do really cool, sophisticated sites. But just the up and running
part, it was super important to me. So by default, you can point it at
a package or set of Python files or something and say, generate docs around that. And it will look
for doc strings and so on, and then generate some kind of hierarchical.
Yeah, exactly. And we tested it quite a bit on different package layouts, like different
packaging systems. And it seems to introspect pretty well based on all sorts of variation.
And we do test this a lot. So the promise is that it does give you something.
And you can also create just more static site type stuff as well, yeah?
Yeah. Oh, absolutely. Yeah, you can.
Yeah, I think the user guide's a good example. Like, if you click the expandable
thing in the top left.
Yeah, everything's so zoomed. Yeah, everything's so zoomed on my little small streaming
screen. So yeah, the user guide got it.
That's, it's nice. The user guide's just a folder in the repo with files in it.
But it's nice, like, that puts up this, like, yeah, more kind of general bit of content,
where it's not your API reference, which is like each individual function explained,
but a more general kind of guide, kind of like a bigger, higher level, like introduction to the
package. But it's nice that, to your point, like, can you have more general kind of content?
It's nice, this is just a folder in the repo. So getting started with the user guide's like,
super fast.
Yeah, and this site is like a demonstration, we're showing like the great docs site,
and we're just looking at it. And you can just add another directory, and like recipes at the
top nav. That's just another directory. And we sort of declared it in our configuration file.
So you can just create something similar to a user guide. But we sort of treat a user guide
as a sort of like a first class thing. Because we, well, I'm a little bit opinionated about
how sites, these docs sites should be. So it kind of serves as a model. So like, the idea is that
if someone sees this and says, yeah, I would like something like this, then like, great docs would
be a good fit. You just have sort of emulate what we have here, do a few things, and you've
pretty much got it beyond the simple sort of like init, and then like build, you can just go a
little bit beyond. Yeah, talk. Yeah, sitting here talking to you makes me think, you know,
I've got some open source projects, I really should have better docs with them. Maybe,
maybe I'll try working on them with great docs. That would be really fun.
Oh, yeah. And I love your feedback. I'm always looking for like ideas and feedback.
Right now, I'm not gonna make a big deal of it. But I'm looking for users, because it's a brand
new project. So like, feedback is a bit scant at this point. So yeah, let me know how it goes.
Yeah, I will definitely. One of the things that's nice here that I'm noticing is it's got a lot of
Yeah, I will definitely.
One of the things that's nice here that I'm noticing
is it's got a lot of elements of the display
that go beyond just standard markdown
that I think are really nice.
Like, for example, you've got these,
I guess these are probably like little tags or badges.
Yeah, they're actually tags, right.
Yeah, and then also you've got a tabbed UI for, like,
here's how you install it on Mac, Linux, Windows,
but in the same little area, right?
You just, like, click the tab for your OS.
Yeah, we call those tab sets in Quarto.
They're like a Quarto special, really.
Yeah.
They just come part and parcel with Quarto.
Yeah, sweet.
So, yeah, I feel like you can do some nice authorship beyond that.
Like, when I was working on my book,
I'm like, I want to write it in markdown,
but I also want to have these little callouts
or, like, an action or, you know, the little sidebar.
Like, how in the heck am I going to get that
to come out of Pandoc, you know what I mean?
Yeah, yeah.
I eventually got it to work by basically getting
a little pre-parser that would just turn those into HTML
and allow the markdown to have HTML, but.
I think that's what makes a good user guide a good user guide.
We actually show, like, not just, like, show the code,
but actually show the results, and you can totally do that.
You know, with a good user guide,
and that's what I try to demonstrate here
in the Great Docs User Guide, that we have these things.
Here's how they look.
You can have these, too.
Yeah, yeah, that definitely looks good.
That's the one thing, too, with Quarto,
that, like, if I had to make the case for Quarto
for a lot of people doing documentation,
it's that it's really easy to run code.
Running code is kind of, like, most of Quarto's game,
that it's a, you author using a QMD.
It's essentially a markdown file,
but your code blocks can be executed.
So it's really inconvenient for docs,
like, being able to include code snippets with their,
and then they get run, and their outputs are there.
So that's kind of the impetus, I think, in this case
for Quarto, is doing, like, really easy execution of code.
It's possible in other tools,
and I know MakeDocStrings, who I think its author
is working with Zensicle now, too,
but, like, they've created a lot of good ways
for you to be able to do this as well, like execute code,
but I do think that's one area
where people stub their toe a lot,
is, like, oh, like, if I'm Polars or Pandas,
or if I'm a DataFrame library,
I probably want a lot of examples,
and then you get stuck in this, like, funny dance,
like, how do I execute the code for my examples?
And so I think tools like Quarto
are really kind of aimed at that use case.
Like, you're a person running code
and generating reports, you know,
that have code and that produce graphs and tables and-
Yeah, and I think the examples, like, being executable
made the great tables examples really powerful.
You can see the code for a table
and then see the table right below,
like, in the actual, like, site,
which is, we didn't have to paste that in.
It was basically just generated right there.
Yeah, that's amazing.
Which is actually incredible.
You can put pros around it as well,
so it's like, it reads just like a little mini guide
in each docstring.
Does it run at build time,
or does it somehow run in the website?
Oh, build time, at build time.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
But you can also-
WebAssembly or something fun like that?
No.
You could do that, you could do that.
Yeah, another nice thing is you can freeze it.
So, like, if you have a bit of code that,
or, like, let's say you have a blog post
and you don't want to rerun it every time,
because, like, over the years,
maybe you just, you, like,
know the code's gonna get out of date
or it takes a long time to run.
You can do something called freeze.
You can quarter freeze it.
And that essentially, like, caches the outputs
so that you can re-render it
without executing the code every time.
So that's useful.
Like, GreatTables, we have kind of a growing log of blog posts
and we don't want to re-execute them every time
because that starts to get pretty time-consuming.
So we can just freeze their outputs
and then they generate super fast.
Another reason you might want to freeze it
is you're accessing live data off an API or website
and you want to talk about the results.
And if it changes, like, all of a sudden,
your pros is like, why are you talking about this?
It doesn't say that.
Like, well, it used to when I did it.
Yeah, you might imagine, like, a benchmark section example
if it runs a long time
or you're just accessing some keys on your personal machine.
Absolutely, freezing is great for that.
You basically froze stuff on your personal computer
and you're just like, you know, sending it off to like CI.
Yeah, yeah.
And I think there's like a million,
there's also like a million of these things
that you encounter when you start generating doc sites
or like personal content, which is like,
yeah, maybe I don't want to run some stuff.
Maybe I want to like include a snippet
from one thing somewhere else.
Or maybe I want to do like all kinds of,
like output customization.
I just feel like there's a million little boxes to check.
So that's one, I mean, one other reason we use Cordo
is we belong to the company that created Cordo.
But I think those like little pieces of detail
for people generating like scientific documents
and stuff goes a long way.
And it's pretty wild too,
because Cordo has a pretty big extension system as well,
like pretty active.
So there's like ways, I mean,
besides like different output types,
there's like extensions and different types of extensions
to like different classes of extensions.
So it goes really deep.
Yeah, Cordo is really neat.
And you all keep talking about Cordo
because it's the foundation
of what's happening with Great Tables, right?
It's been a while since it was,
it's been a while since I had JJ and Carlos
on the podcast to talk about Cordo.
But so maybe just give folks a bit of a refresher
of what is Cordo
and then how that relates back to Great Tables.
Yeah, so Cordo is like an open source publishing system.
So you can make things like sites,
like documents, like books, for instance.
You can make presentations.
There's probably a few more I'm missing.
And it's cross-language as well.
And like code cells.
So it has computational notebooks is what they call them
because they have cells
which are basically computational cells,
which can accept, which have different engines.
So you can like say, like run some R code,
run some Python, some Julia, what have you,
many other things as well.
And then you can stitch them,
you know, basically render them into documents
using Pandoc for the most part
and probably other things too for different output types.
And it just really, batteries included,
has things like you just see on the site,
citations, cross-refs, you know, it's got all essentially.
And so how it relates to Cordoc and to Great Docs,
we're using Cordoc as like, you know,
but not really.
Like I think with Cordoc, it's,
the way I see it is like,
and correct me if I'm wrong, Michael,
Cordoc, you're creating a reference API,
but you're still basically using Cordo.
You're within the Cordo itself.
You're still creating the Cordo config.
But with Great Docs, it's kind of like Cordo
is a bit sort of like a,
we're using it obviously,
but you don't have to know a lot about Cordo.
You can basically get by with just a few things you see,
you know, in like the user guide
and not have to like go deeply into Cordo.
It sort of like hides it a little bit
or doesn't really advertise it as much,
even though we use it a lot.
Just for some context.
Yeah, I mentioned before I developed a tool
called Cordoc,
which is another documentation generator for Cordo.
So just to clarify like the context,
yeah, like Cordoc is a much more kind of like low level,
no frills.
So like the IBIS project uses it.
So that's another pretty big Python tool,
but it's like very like simple.
It's more about like dump your API reference
and then you're responsible for like customizing
your website.
And so it's for people who really wanna like be in control
and set it all up.
I think Rich is kind of underselling.
I think GreatDocs is just dripping in style.
I think that's one of the keys
is it's made to be kind of like an all-in-one,
something really nice out of the box that's opinionated.
But I just wanted to clarify for context,
Cordodoc is another tool outside of Cordo.
So I know we've checked a lot of tools out,
but one thing that's interesting is I know,
like when we look at GreatDocs,
it's easy to see like some of the stuff that jumps out,
but there's actually, I think to Rich's credit,
there's a ton of like little things inside GreatDocs
that you almost don't notice until you need them.
Like there's a million little pieces to doc sites
and some of them are actually pretty intriguing.
Like if you go to the GreatDocs API reference,
I think it kind of like speaks to Rich's style
that he's included a ton of stuff out of the box for this,
including this little like filter bar.
So if you click on the top left,
you can sort of like filter on the page
for different pieces.
That's like, yeah.
I think for just to illustrate the difference,
so Cordodoc is a really bare bones tool.
It's like we generate an API for you.
GreatDocs, like this thing, this filter bar
where you can like type in it
and it shows you live on the page.
Like it filters your reference items.
That's just pure Rich,
just like wilding out on what docs could be.
And I think there are like a million little examples
of this kind of in GreatDocs.
Kind of, yeah.
Because like I find little things that annoy me
and I want to fix them.
But, and so this is my,
this is almost like a Python site generator
for me in lots of ways.
But I'm hoping that other people
feel these little pain points as well.
I've certainly felt it.
I've gone to documentation sites
and searched for stuff on there.
And then you see a little spinner searching, searching.
Static site, what are we doing?
Why am I waiting?
This doesn't make any sense to me, but okay.
Yeah.
Even the CLI button, like, oh, sorry.
If you click that,
that's like if you have a command line interface
for your tool, which is so hot today,
like AI loves command line interfaces.
Cloud code's just bash executing everything.
You know, a lot of people have CLIs.
I think it also speaks a lot to Registar
that he created this spot for your CLI docs to live.
Very important.
And then at the top right, if you look,
there's like a copy.
You can copy the whole page to Markdown
or view it as Markdown.
I never would have thought of that.
Like to me, I would never go that far
to give people something nice.
I don't know if I'm just like a chromogeny engineer.
I think Rich is just dreaming up like, I don't know,
different ways you could interact with docs,
copy the page to Markdown.
And I don't doubt that it's like incredibly useful.
To me, this strikes me as like-
I think it's very useful, yeah.
Yeah.
When I saw that table graph for Great Tables,
like breaking apart the table into every little piece,
this strikes me as Rich again,
like imagining every little thing a doc site could do.
So I think that's what I'm so kind of gassed up about.
Yeah, that's delightful.
And we're gonna come back to AI stuff later,
but we don't have that much time left, honestly,
you guys, we've been talking,
and not making a lot of progress,
because it's really, we're just diving into it.
Docs talk.
It's so fun.
I know, it's so fun.
But I can easily see I'm working on a project,
and I've got Claude or some codex or whatever,
and it's just not getting it for a certain function.
Just go to the docs, hit copy pages Markdown,
and just go, no AI, this is the docs, read it.
Because giving it a Markdown result of what this is,
versus all the nav and all the stuff,
and it's trying to understand
what's the essence of the page,
if you tell it to just go to the page,
it's really, really different.
Yeah, it's a bit more immediate, I think.
And also you can change the URL,
if you really want to, to .md,
and just give it the URL.
So many ways to do it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, I love that.
So instead of html.md.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's really cool.
So if you, you or Claude Code are reading the docs,
you know, a lot of good, a lot of good stuff.
Yeah, here's some tokens.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, that's cool.
Did I do that for TalkPython?
I think I did.
Yeah, if you do that on TalkPython, by the way,
you can do, just put .md on the end of any episode name,
and it gives you the markdown equivalent of that as well.
So which is all the rage.
Yeah, so I mean, we're on the same vibes here.
I'm loving it, you know what I mean?
Yeah, and it might even help for context.
I'd be curious to hear your,
like when you added that markdown,
and some of your motivation for markdownifying your site.
I didn't do it for people.
I did it for AI and SEO.
For the machine stuff.
Yeah, for the machine.
So I added a, if I could type,
I did an llms.txt to try to get the AIs
to understand the podcast better.
And some of the things that I gave it
was this ability to just put markdown at the end,
but also I added like a CLI and an MCP
and different things for an API, search API.
And I'm like, okay, AI,
there's 7.5 million words of content over 11 years.
I want you to know about it and be able to use it.
How many ways can I imagine giving something to it?
And this render as markdown was certainly one of them.
That's great.
Yeah, that's awesome.
I also added some silly stuff that's like for,
just for me, because I've got, for example,
I've got to update, say, the YouTube recommendations.
So, or listings after the live stream,
I want them to have like links and stuff.
So I can say .youtube on the end,
and it gives me the contents for like the YouTube renders.
So it kind of was building on this,
like how can I help myself be more efficient,
but also a machine?
So anyway, that's the story.
This is where it's like Doc's workflow really, right?
Fits in nicely.
Yeah.
So, you know, circling back around,
I'm really impressed with some of these little nuances
that are super nice.
Yeah.
I think that's great.
Yeah, thank you.
I'll go further on this.
It's basically just nicing up the docs
and make them good for humans,
but also consumable by LLMs or digits.
It's just, Rich, it's a fad.
We don't really need to worry about it.
It's going to go away.
The bubble's going to burst.
We can just, we can just ignore it.
It's going to be fine.
No.
So let's talk,
I want to talk about a couple of things here.
So let's just do like a real quick,
little walkthrough of maybe getting started with this.
Because it's honestly not a whole lot to get started,
but give us this,
one of you all walk us through the quick start,
just so people kind of know what's involved.
Yeah.
So really that command, like great docs init,
that'll make the file that is basically
what you need for the build.
And with a lot of testing,
it should work on many different like Python package,
like layouts and types.
So you just need that.
Of course, yeah, install great docs,
install cordo as well.
So we got that as well before that.
But once you have those things,
it should do what it says on the screen,
basically show you stuff in the terminal,
which is all positive.
It's creating that great docs.yaml file.
And it should be pretty minimal what's in there.
It should actually also be a little bit dynamic.
Based on your project,
it'll craft like the correct great docs.yaml file
or the config file.
And then you could go ahead and customize,
but you might just jump to building your documentation
because that's the next easiest thing.
It's just another command, great docs build.
And what you get is a great hyphen docs directory
in your working directory.
And that contains like the site folder,
but you don't really have to worry about that
because you have another command called great docs preview,
which will basically launch like a web server
and then put the site in your default browser,
basically just like let you see the site locally.
And then because I'm a big fan
of letting people know what's going on.
So it should be totally a black box.
I give on this page, like a structure,
the basic structure of how it should look
on your working directory.
But that's kind of it.
And I believe the next step for most people
will just be getting this on CI if they're satisfied
and then just working from there,
like modifying their initialization,
not initialization, their config file
to give the site more customization personality
and there'll be authoring guides and things like that.
Very cool.
So you've got the really nice watch feature.
So great docs build dash dash watch.
Yes.
Which feels very Hugo to me, you know,
like you're gonna build it so you can look at it,
but then you wanna edit it.
So just if you see any changes, just rebuild, right?
Yeah, exactly.
Small sites will build fast,
but this is way faster, obviously.
So yeah, this is pretty essential for iterating,
especially initially, yeah.
Yeah.
And what about this version?
So this is an interesting aspect of the project.
Versions.
Well, essentially you may have, you know,
multiple tagged versions of your site.
And this is kind of like a wild thing.
You can have different documentation sites
based on your version.
Cause you have, for instance, new things in your API.
Right.
People maybe know that from Python
where you can go up here and drop down.
Exactly.
So this is kind of like just seeing like certain versions
of your site and it gives you a selector
on the great docs site itself.
We have a selector, which is maximal.
It has like every single version from the very first
and you can cruise in there and you'll see
that there'll be way less in the earliest versions.
Like the, if you look at the user guide for 0.1,
which is a little icon, a little scary.
It's unsupported.
If you look at the user guide, it's pretty sparse.
Like it's, you know, it's not as long as the other one.
And if you look at the reference as well,
it'll have less items.
So it's aware of like what's available in which versions.
And so you sort of set that up yourself
or you can just do it through that command.
Is that based on get tags or what is that?
Based on get tags.
Yeah, that's right.
Okay.
I was wondering how does it even know?
Yeah, you have to give it some information.
Like you have to of course get the tags,
but if you actually configure it to do what it's doing here,
like make the site,
you just change your configuration to have,
it's basically just like a small config that you have to do.
And you can set labels and things like that.
Can I wild card it
or have it somehow pick up all the versions?
I mean, you don't wanna pick up all tags,
but it'd be like star dot star.
I don't think we have version expressions like that yet.
Yeah.
Not yet, okay.
You know, throw it in there.
I'm just thinking if I have a project
with 27 versions over time.
Yeah, you probably wouldn't do it
through like this interface, like great docs build.
This is just for like a very quick comparison.
Got it.
But if you would do it,
like you probably put that in the config file
and you'd have to manually edit those.
But I think with a small app or something like that
would be better.
And there's an API, of course,
if you wanna just have a control.
Yeah, it's kind of, you wouldn't do this,
but it's just, I threw it in there just.
Well, probably because your commands use that, right?
Yeah, exactly.
Might as well just let people know.
Just being transparent, I suppose, yeah.
Okay.
Where do we wanna go next?
Let's cover just a couple of remaining things here
while we got time.
What about open source sustainability?
Like I know you all at Posit are doing a lot of things
to open source your work and so on.
Yeah, well, we're pretty much like full time
doing open source work.
So essentially, and so I think these projects
have long life cycles with the same maintainer
for long periods of time,
which is great for project stability and things like that.
And we're accountable for issues that come in
and for releases and making sure it's not dead projects
all the way down or whatever.
So I think that's a great thing.
And for instance, like Great Tables,
I've been at it since the beginning,
GT, which is where it came from, since 2017.
So I think that helps a lot,
adds a lot of credibility to these projects
that are not just being abandoned.
There's no fear of it being abandoned or things like that.
There's a person there, at least.
Yeah, and I think Posit's found
an interesting business model
that's been long term sustaining,
but still allows you, as you said,
to sort of work in open source.
Maybe speak to that, either one of you real quick.
Michael, would you?
Sure.
Yeah, it's really interesting
and it's almost like not diving crazy deep
in doing a podcast.
My favorite thing to say to people is that,
like we have a really large open source engineering team,
dozens of open source engineers.
People often ask like, how does Posit pay the bills
for people to work on open source?
My favorite thing to say is like,
we have a bunch of boring enterprise tools.
And no shade on Posit,
I actually think that this is the best case scenario.
Like we have a lot of tools that solve
really painful problems if you're an enterprise.
They could be useful in other settings,
but it's like, how do I run a report every day?
Or how do I host like Jupyter Notebooks
or VS Code for my, say like data team or RStudio?
Those essentially pay the bills.
That's Posit connected to Posit teams.
You've got a team of data scientists,
but you don't necessarily have a DevOps team,
but you still wanna have their stuff running reliably, right?
Yeah.
Yeah, and it's a hard problem.
If you're a company, right?
These are kind of tricky problems.
Or you have like a really mean IT team.
These, a cruel IT team could like hamstring you for years.
But that's just to say like,
we get to work on open source because these tools exist.
And I think Posit exists,
I think because the maintainers care
so much about open source.
I will say in terms of sustainability,
one interaction I've really liked over the years
is like in the docs realm,
there's this person, I only know him as Pawel Moi.
His GitHub handle, I think it's Timothy or Timothy
in France, I think.
But he maintains the tools upstream of tools
like PortaDoc and GreatDocs.
And we've interacted a bit in the past
where I've done PRs on his tools.
One's called Griff.
And I think that's such an important part
of sustainability too,
is that he works on a documentation tool,
make doc strings,
but we're all able to collaborate on his tool Griff
that actually powers all of our documentation sites.
So I think that's a really important piece.
I think to your point about being at PyCon
and seeing people,
I think us as open source maintainers,
chatting and even contributing
and working on say like upstream tools
is a really important part
of keeping the ecosystem healthy and sustainable.
We're not like multiple doc tools competing to degree.
I do think they compete,
but ultimately like we're working on open source
because we're passionate.
And I think it helps to collaborate
on our kind of like shared tools.
Yeah, 100% agree, very cool.
Now, Rich, you mentioned that it's a pretty new project.
Yeah.
Where are we going?
What's next?
What's on the roadmap?
Yeah, lots of things.
I even have a roadmap on the site if anyone's interested,
but I think it would be like a lot more like
documentation for different things, like new things.
Like the other day I was suggested
to create documentation for MCP servers.
I was like, good idea.
We don't really have that.
And it's pretty easy to document, it's JSON essentially.
So we can take that apart,
parse that and present something.
That's a good point because if you look at the MCP servers,
they don't have structure in the way
that traditional projects do, right?
They don't just have like a separate function
for each thing.
They've got this kind of weird invocation entry point
where you pass like the tool you wanna use.
And yeah, it's a little different thing.
Documentation, prompt suggestions, things like that.
So I think we can do a pretty good job there.
The idea is pretty new, but like,
I guess we're, yeah, just trying to be
or go where things are going.
And it'll be a little bit better.
So would that somehow show itself as like
where you've got the API and the CLI?
Was there also be an MCP or what do you think?
It's gonna be a bit crowded.
So I'm rethinking.
I know.
Yeah.
Yeah, I was like, I don't really know what to do.
I think this would be it.
Like, but no, it's not quite it.
There's one or two more things.
So it might be just a dropdown nav on the top,
like a dropdown on the top nav, I'm thinking.
So that's part of what I have to think about.
But there's things like that.
And also like a recent thing we just did,
and this is very new.
So it's almost like it's new enough,
is like skills, like publishing skills
and making them available and making them browsable, right?
So on the grave, it's not top level.
If you go to the first page,
there's like a sidebar on the right,
which gives you a lot of metadata.
And one of the first few things is skills.
And that gives you like a page
on how to install these skills.
So it's kind of like a, almost like a way,
not to just distribute,
but a way to sort of like get a hold of skills.
And there's a nice little sort of like disclosure there.
Install these skills.
It gives you instructions on how to do such things.
And you can just browse the skills below
and see what's there.
You might just take bits of them, make your own skill,
or you might just say, no, these all look good.
I'll just follow these instructions
and install them for my project or globally.
We're trying to make that easy.
Yeah, it's super cool.
Yeah, kind of expose these things, yeah.
Yeah, that kind of brings me to the last thing
that I want to talk about is the AI-fication.
And by that, I don't mean, how do I,
are you using AI to write it or not?
Like I imagine there's some degree of that or whatever,
but if I am a person with a project,
a package or something that I want to document,
AI is really good at going like,
well, let me pull out all these pieces
and then like sketch some stuff out for you.
And I can see now that you pointed me in the right direction
that there's a whole AI section,
like how do AIs work with great docs, right?
And so you've got the llms.txt, which is really nice.
I referenced that before.
People don't know there's an,
this comes from, I believe from Jeremy,
yeah, Jeremy Howard.
Yeah, that's right.
Yeah, we looked at this closely, yeah.
Putting, yeah, so did I, and I find it super interesting.
Like this, the idea is that if you,
you know, there's a robots.txt and a sitemap.xml.
These are standard web things on sites
that humans rarely use to get any value from,
but machines and traditionally search engines
really, really do.
And so, well, what do we put for AI to make it better?
And so what we're doing is we're putting
this llms.txt file that describes in Markdown
to the llms, like how you can better work with this.
So with that, you all have that, right?
So you've got your llms.txt and the full one.
You know, this is not something I'm doing.
Maybe I need to do a full one.
This one's interesting.
It's a lot.
So basically it's the entire bit of documentation
distilled down, not distilled,
but like written as one file, essentially.
All doc strings mash together, you might say,
including guide material as well.
So that's one.
Yeah, and you've got these skills as well,
which is looking super interesting
and also pretty neat, the CLI that you've created.
Well, a couple of things on that.
First of all, that it will actually install the skills.
Yeah, so if you're an author,
you would just use great docs, install,
skill install, and then maybe the name of your library.
Nice.
For the people, that's what other people see on their site.
I think it's an interesting piece.
Because if I'm, I have to admit,
I haven't seen the skills piece a lot,
but if I'm understanding, Rich, too,
this means great docs is also for like,
kind of all users, right?
Like people who are interested in reading
or consuming docs or using it with AI.
Is that right?
Yeah, yeah.
I'd say so.
That's kind of where we're going more and more.
Yeah, so it looks like you're really leaning
into making great docs something that works well
if you're trying to generate docs
and maintain them with AI, right?
If you point your agent at this site,
it should be able to find these things pretty quickly.
And you can actually like use tools.
Like there's one called whatdoagency.runtime.app.
Just search it up.
You can put it in your URL,
and it'll show you what pieces are picked up
by different agents.
It actually simulates it really nicely.
And I found, just to validate things,
that different agents do pick up LLMs.text, LLMs.full,
and there's other little.
549, cli, Great Docs, Great Tables, gt, pkgdown, Quarto